Finding Aid for the Albert W. Harris Papers
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Albert W. Harris Papers
undated
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0193
0.42 Linear Feet
Biographical/Historical Sketch:
A. W. Harris was born in Nashville in 1839 to William C. and Fannie Harris. William C. Harris was the one-time editor of The Republican Banner newspaper before its incorporation into The American and finally The Tennessean. As a young man, A.W. Harris worked as a wholesale shoe salesman until the outbreak of the Civil War in which he enlisted as a private in Company A, Rock City Guards, First Tennessee Regiment. He moved up in the ranks, achieving the position of major by the closing of the war. Once released from military service, Major Harris briefly lived in Mississippi where he conducted a plantation until his eventual return home to Nashville, Tennessee where he married Fannie Wilson, daughter of Dr. J.R. Wilson and had three children, Mary Lou, W.O. and Albert W. Harris. His youngest, Albert W. Harris would later become a student at Vanderbilt University receiving his M.D. in 1901 and later serving as a Captain in the Vanderbilt Medical Unit with the American Army in France and the Army for Occupation in Germany during WWI. After WWI, Dr. Albert W. Harris would serve on the medical faculty at Vanderbilt University as a professor of Clinical Neurology and Psychiatry until his death in 1941.
In Nashville, Major A.W. Harris would first work as a clerk and later an assistant cashier at the Third National Bank until its consolidation as the American National Bank in 1883. At such time, Harris would be elected as the Chief Executive Officer, accepting the position but not a pay raise, believing it was unethical when the country was facing economic turmoil. In 1884, he was elected to serve on the Board of Directors. For the next few years, A.W. Harris suffered from what was called an “affusion of the blood” most likely a form of apoplexy or hemorrhaging causing fits that were recorded in local newspapers for their violence. Nevertheless, and despite his doctor’s recommendations, A.W. Harris continued to serve the Nashville area diligently and tirelessly. In the years leading up to his death he aided in numerous estate disputes, wrote articles on the state of banking in the area and aided in the organizational formation and managed records for the Trotting Horse Breeders Association. On July 23rd, 1898, Major Harris experienced a coughing fit that ruptured an artery, causing a hemorrhage which resulted in his death.
Scope and Content of Collection:
The A.W. Harris Papers are contained within one Hollinger box of 25 folders. The collection is primarily composed of the financial transactions, various correspondences, newsletters and horse pedigree papers from the Trotting Horse Breeders Association. The collection holds eight folders of receipts from the years 1861-1874, those of his wife Fannie A. Wilson, his in-law relatives Thomas B. Wilson, and W.L. Wilson; showcasing the sale of domestic goods, real estate, labor and livestock. Some purchases are accompanied by reserve stamps from the Civil War, and are noteworthy for their representation of 19th century local economics and business life within the Nashville area as well as broader Tennessee. The collection also holds seven folders of correspondence between the Harris and Wilson families between 1867-1895. These correspondences pertain to private matters, various business transactions of the family businesses, as well as the incoming correspondences of Temple O. Harris and A.W. Harris. Two folders containing documents, newspaper clippings, and records concerning agriculture and animal husbandry from the years 1867-1873. Four folders containing bank receipts from the Fourth National Bank from the years 1872-1873. The remaining four folders contain an assessment list issued by Davidson county in 1874, a newspaper clipping regarding veteran pensions, Nashville local business documents, and the personal notes of A.W. Harris.
- Receipts: W.L. Wilson, 1861-1867 (Folder 1)
- Receipts: Thomas B. Wilson, 1865-1868 (Folder 2)
- Receipts: Mrs. Fannie A. Wilson, 1866-1867 (Folder 3)
- Receipts, 1866-1874 (Folder 4)
- A.W. Harris’ Personal and Business Receipts, 1865-1871 (Folder 5)
- A.W. Harris’ Personal and Business Receipts, 1872 (Folder 6)
- A.W. Harris’ Personal and Business Receipts, 1873 (Folder 7)
- A.W. Harris’ Personal and Business Receipts, 1874 and undated (Folder 8)
- Miscellaneous Correspondence: 1870-1875- stockholder meetings, notice of stock sales, direction of future payments, receipt for a subscription to the Christian Observer, various envelopes with stamps. (Folder 9)
- Unidentified Letters and Essays: undisclosed and undated letter to a young person describing well wishes and advice for their life, untitled and incomplete essay fragments, chart. (Folder 10)
- Incoming Correspondence of the Harris Family (1869-1873)- Including J.E. Harris (1869), D.B. Harris (1870-1873) from the office of Warren Mitchell & Co. Provision and Commission Merchants, including a Gift to the Public Library of Kentucky, J.O.H (1871, undated), two unclear letters (1870, 1871), and W.O. Harris (unclear date). (Folder 11)
- Letters Regarding the Wilson’s Properties- T.B. Wilson (1868-1873) and W.L. Wilson (1873). (Folder 12)
- Miscellaneous Letters: Addressed to A.W. Harris (1867-1870) discussing funds, property, sales, and personal matters (Folder 13)
- Miscellaneous Letters: Addressed to A.W. Harris (1871-1895) discussing funds, property, sales, and personal matters (Folder 14)
- Various Incoming Correspondences of Temple O. Harris (1870-1873) (Folder 15)
- Documents and Clippings Concerning Agriculture and Animal Husbandry (1867-1871)- Official and unofficial documents concerning the sale of land, agricultural equipment, produce, “best time to plant the following seeds” chart, letters, ledgers, memos and receipts. (Folder 16)
- Documents and Clippings Concerning Agriculture and Animal Husbandry (1872-1873)- Official and unofficial documents concerning the breeding stock of stallions, cattle herd catalogue, newspaper clipping describing the papers released on Agricultural, Horticultural, etc. on file at the office of the State Agricultural Society in this city, letters, ledgers, memos and receipts. (Folder 17)
- Bank Checks from the Fourth National Bank signed by A.W. Harris, 1872 (Folder 18)
- Bank Checks from the Fourth National Bank signed by A.W. Harris, February-June 1873 (Folder 19)
- Bank Checks from the Fourth National Bank signed by A.W. Harris, July-November 1873 (Folder 20)
- Bank Checks from the Fourth National Bank signed by A.W. Harris, 1874 (Folder 21)
- Assessment Law: Davidson County, 5th district, 1874 (Folder 22)
- Newspaper clipping regarding the pensions of Veterans who fought in the battles between Texas and Mexico / on the reverse holds a quote about farming from Mark Twain (Folder 23)
- Nashville local business documents: The relocation of a clothing store and two Nashville business cards. (Folder 24)
- Notes (Folder 25)